Miscellaneous Benjamin Franklin Collections 1710-1822 Mss.B.F85.misc
American Philosophical Society
- Benjamin Franklin Miscellaneous Collection, 1710-1793; Mss.B.F85.[numeral]; 531 items
  - Petition to Benjamin Franklin, president, Supreme Executive Council, 1787 Oct. 18; ALS, 2p. Contains A.N.S. by B. Franklin to the Secretary of Council.; Lea, Thomas
    Petition in the case of Peter January, a bankrupt.
  - Letter to M. de Chaumont; Philad, 1787 October 22; ALS, 1p.; Franklin, Benjamin, 1706-1790
    Partly in French.
    Printed: Smyth, v.9,620.
  - Order to David Rittenhouse to pay David hanna £20.10 for services rendered, 1787 October 7; DS, 2p.; Supreme executive council, Pennsylvania
    Presented by Mrs. Arthur Bloch as a forgary from her husband's estate, July 1954.
  - Letter to Thomas Short, Edinburgh, 1787 December 5; ALS, 1p.; Franklin, Benjamin, 1706-1790
    On same sheet with letter from Theodotia Short to BF; Sept.13, 1787
    Sends letter from Mrs. Theodosia Short about her family.
  - Description of the tapid bath made use of by his Excellency Benjamin Franklin, Governor of Pensylvania.., 1787 December; Cy, 1p. and 2 illus.; Franklin, Benjamin, 1706-1790
    From original in Robert R. Logan family papers, deposited 1949 at the Library Co. of Philadelphia. Permission required for reproduction.
  - Petition on the part of Thomas Willing, as president of the Bank of Norht America, to Benjamin Franklin, President of the Supreme Executive Council of Pennsylvania, against Joshua Pusey, a bankrupt.., 1787; DCy, 3 leaves; Willing, Thomas, 1731-1821
    Contains copy of portion of bankruptcy proceedings against Samuel Garrigues.
  - Letter to Charles Vaughan, 1788 February 12; ALS, 1p.; Franklin, Benjamin, 1706-1790
    Settlement of Dr. Ingenhousz's account with John Williams. Comments on the Opposition to the Constitution - "America is too Enlightened to be enslav'd... the happiness of its People is less in canger from an Excess of Power in the Governors, than from the Defect of due Obedience... in the Governed.
    For draft of these quotation, see Franklin Papers, vol, XXXVI,14.
  - Letter to St. John Crevecoeur, 1788 February 16, 17; Photostat, 2p.; Franklin, Benjamin, 1706-1790
    Portion dated Feb. 16 printed in Smyth, v.9, 636. The P.S. dated Feb. 17 comments on Fitch's steamboat and Mr. Rittenhouse's opinion of it.
    From film in L.C. Original in volume of letters to St. John de Crèvecoeur owned by M. Louis St. John de Crèvecoeur, La Plagne, Moncesquiousur Lesse (Gers), France.
  - Petition to Benjamin Franklin, asking for a pardon so that he might emigrate "to the back Countrys", 1788 Mar. 10; DS, 4p.; Phetty, Philip
    Not in Pennsylvania Archives of above date. With 34 signatures asking that the petition be acted upon favorably; end: "Read in Council June 4th 1788..."
  - Patent issued to Matthias Dibler for tract of land in Dauphin co, 1788 March 13; DS, parchment seal.; Pennsylvania. Supreme Executive Council
  - Letter to Benjamin Franklin, president, Supreme Executive Council, 1788 May 5; ALS, 2p.; Craig, Thomas
    Disputes the fact that he opposed the execution of a criminal named John Brown.
    Printed: Penna. archives.s.2.276-277.
  - Letter to Mr. Wilcke, 1788 May 7; TCy, 1p.; Franklin, Benjamin, 1706-1790
    Sends Vol.1 and 2 of the Transactions of the APS.
    Presented by I.B. Cohen, March 1954.
    From original in possession of the Royal Swedish academy of sciences.
  - Letter to Secretary of Councils, 1788 May 13; Photostat. 1p.; Franklin, Benjamin, 1706-1790
  - Commission to Peter Stephen DuPonceau as notary, tabellion and interpreter of foreign languages for the Commonwealth, 1788 August 20; 1p. Seal; Pennsylvania. Supreme Executive Council
    Attached to this document are certifications to the fact that E. Dutilh and Co of Philadelphia have been appointed attorneys for Mr. Gaspard Solicoffre in a suit against Messrs. Zolikoffer and Messonnier of Baltimore; Feb. 28,1788, August 18,1788.
    French and English translation. 8p.
    Printed D.S: B. Franklin, president
  - Letter to Mr. [Robert] Aitken, 1789 January 17; Letterpress Cy, 2p.; Franklin, Benjamin, 1706-1790
    Relative to Vol. 1 of A.P.S. Transactions.
  - Letter to Matthew Carey, 1789 February 9; AL, 1p.; Franklin, Benjamin, 1706-1790
    Encloses Remarks on the Albany Plan which he may publish in the Museum, but not under Franklin's signature.
    The Remarks were published in Carey's American Museum, v.5, April 1739, p.368.
    Printed: APS Library Bulletin for 1943, p. 73.
  - Letter to [Catherine Ray] Greene, 1789 March 2; Letterpress Cy, 2p.; Franklin, Benjamin, 1706-1790
    Printed: Smyth, v.10,3.
    Printed: APS Library Bulletin for 1946, p.31.
    Printed: Roelker's Franklin-Greene Correspondence, p.135
  - Letter to [Jane Mecom], 1789 April 27; Photo., 1p.; Franklin, Benjamin, 1706-1790
    Concern about reliability of post, health and finances of Mecom. Mentions C. Greene.
    1. Greene, Catharine Ray, 1731-1794. 2. Postal service - U.S. I. BF chron. II. [Mecom, Jane], 1712-1793.
  - Letter to unidentified recipient, 1789 October 23; ALS, 1p.; Franklin, Benjamin, 1706-1790
    Relative to settlement on bond entered into with Mr. Grace in 1748.
    (The letter may be Written to Thomas Franklin, Phila. merchant; see letters in Franklin Papers)
  - to Catharine Wistar, 1790 Aug. 10; Wistar, B
  - [Epitaph, in German], ca. 1793-1794; D. 1p.; Franklin, Benjamin, 1706-1790
    Not same translation as used in the 1780 Dresden edition, nor the 1794 and 1802 Weimar editions of the Works.
  - to Catharine Bache, [1797]; Wistar, Caspar
  - to Catharine Bache, 1815 Mar. 18; Wistar, Caspar
  - n.d., Photostat, 3p.
    "A discussion of that interesting question whether if the United States should be compelled to choose its side in ye present European contest, on which side its interest would require it should engage? To which is added, some impartial thoughts upon the rights of neutrals and the history of the conduct of belligerents on this subject. Notes by B.F."
    All in B. Vaughan's hand.
    Consists of answers (?) to nine questions.
  - Graphic chart showing the Eighteenth Century events, with special reference to Benjamin Franklin, D. 1p. 12-1/2x21.
    (see Franklin pamphlets, no.4.)
  - Letter to [Benjamin Franklin], n.d. (Aug 20); ALS, 3p.; Cramer, Mme Delon(?)
    Is taking care of B. F.Bache, due to the death of her husband's brother.
  - Epitaph, n.d.; Photostat 2p.; Franklin, Benjamin, 1706-1790
  - The Character of Charles the 12th of Sweeden, n.d.; Photocopy, 1p.; Franklin, Benjamin, 1706-1790
    From originals in the Julia Rush Biddle Henry Coll., Rosenbach Foundation
  - [Shorthand notes], D. 2p.; Franklin, Benjamin, 1706-1790
    May be handwriting of William or William Temple Franklin
  - Cupid and Zephyr. On the breaking of the seventh commandment and wind, D. 56p.; Franklin, Benjamin, 1706-1790
    Contains copies of letters: Franklin to a young man; June 25,1743; and, Franklin to the Royal Society of Brussels.
  - Drawings of the Franklin [electrical?] machine, presented by Franklin to Capt. [Isaac] All, n.d.; Photo, 7 leaves; Franklin, Benjamin, 1706-1790
    Minutes of Committe on Library;Oct. 17 and Dec.12, 1957.
    Presented by Charles T. Henry; Nov. 1960.
  - Epitaph, n.d.; AMs. 1p.; Franklin, Benjamin, 1706-1790
  - Marginalia in Affaires de l'Angleterre et de l'Amerique; Nos. 36 and 38, Photocopy of D. 11 leaves.; Franklin, Benjamin, 1706-1790
    Presented by owner: Eleutherian Mills-Hagley Mills Library; March 1971.
  - Moyens pour d'un grand Empire en faireun petit, Photocopy of D. 14p.; Franklin, Benjamin, 1706-1790
    Photocopy copy presented by owner, Eleutherian Mills-Hagley Mills Library; March 1971.
  - Observations sur l'origine de la Guerre Civile des Colonies Américaines, n.d.; Photocopy of D. 19p.; Franklin, Benjamin, 1706-1790
    Presented by owner, Eleutherian Mills, Hagley Library; March 1971.
  - Recommendation of Pierre Sonnerat for membership in the Royal Society, DS; Franklin, Benjamin, 1706-1790 and J. Osborn
  - to unidentified recipient, June 15.; A.N. in 3d P. Card.; Franklin, Benjamin, 1706-1790
  - Letter to [Matthew] Boulton, n.d. (Friday); Photostat of L. in 3d P. 1p.; Franklin, Benjamin, 1706-1790
    Wishes to consult with Mr. Boulton about a copying press and writing desk.
  - Letter to [Matthew] Bolton (sic), n.d. (Monday); Photostat of A.L. in 3d P. 1p.; Franklin, Benjamin, 1706-1790
    Invitation to dinner. Mentions Abbé Morellet.
  - Letter to W[illiam] Bradford, n.d.; ALS, 2p.; Rivington, James, 1724-1802
    Wishes to forward books for sale in Pennsylvania. Names authors and terms which he says would be advantageous to each.
  - Letter to [Mme Helvetius ?], n.d.; LS, 2p.; Franklin, Benjamin, 1706-1790
    Accepts an invitation for himself and grandson for a visit on Sunday.
  - to [Mary Stevenson] Hewson, n.d.; Fragment of an A.L; Franklin, Benjamin, 1706-1790
  - Letter to [Philip] Mazzei, Sunday; A.L. in 3d P. 1p.; Franklin, Benjamin, 1706-1790
    Unable to be in Versailles on Tuesday.
  - to Mary [Stevenson], Friday Morng.; ALS, 1p.; Franklin, Benjamin, 1706-1790
  - to [Mary Stevenson?], Friday, 2 P.M.; A.L.Signed with initials. 1p.; Franklin, Benjamin, 1706-1790
  - to [Mary Stevenson], Wednesday morning.; ALS, 1p.; Franklin, Benjamin, 1706-1790
  - to Mary Stevenson, Wednesday P.M.; ALS, 1p. (About some of her translations); Franklin, Benjamin, 1706-1790
  - Letter to William Stille:, Sunday. October 1 1786; ALS, 1p. Mutilated.; Franklin, Benjamin, 1706-1790
    In re western wall of house next to Mr. Stille's property.
  - Letter to "My Very good friend", Photostat, 1p.; Franklin, Deborah Read Rogers, 1708-1774
  - Deposition in re Major Peter Colombe, n.d.; ADS; U.S. Board of War
    Certified by Franklin
- Benjamin Franklin Account Books, 1730-1874; Mss.B.F85.f6.numeral; 33 volumes
  Thirty-three complete volumes portraying Franklin's business and personal concerns as well as his work with the Post Office in Philadelphia. These volumes also include a partial account of Franklin's estate and records maintained by Deborah Read Franklin and William Temple Franklin.
  - Account of Expences of my Voyage to England, 1757-1761; 1 vol.; Franklin Benjamin
    This volume contains the records of Franklin's expenditures in going to England in 1757 as well as his expenses while living in London. Some receipts are included herein as are some entries for bills of exchange received. Even more, there are entries for receipt of funds from Speaker Isaac Norris, of Philadelphia, which Franklin invested in government stocks and annuities, etc. This was printed by G. S. Eddy, "Account Book of Benjamin Franklin kept by him during his First Mission to England as Provincial Agent 1757-1762," Pennsylvania Magazine of History and Biography, volume LV (1931), 97-133.
    The Papers of Benjamin Franklin, volume VII, l64-5.
  - Receipt Book, 1742-1764; 1 vol.; Franklin Benjamin
    This is a typical receipt book for payments made to various persons for generally unnamed services or materials. Either Franklin, his wife, or the person receiving payment, wrote that he had received so much money on a given date, and signed the entry.
    The Papers of Benjamin Franklin, volume II, 351-352.
    The last eight pages contain a record of Franklin's income from his business partner, David Hall. Included in the entries is income of money and occasionally the value of books received in lieu of money.
    The Papers of Benjamin Franklin, volume III, 276.
  - Journal, 1764-1774; 1 vol.; Franklin Benjamin
    "The Journal of Benjamin Franklin after his leaving Philadelphia Nov[embe]r. 7. 1764 and during his Residence in London" is a chronological listing of expenses and receipts. This "Journal" is to be used in conjunction with "Ledger; l764?1776, for they were "put in order" by Jonathan Williams, Jr., Franklin's grandnephew and Franklin, kept both volumes thereafter.
    The Papers of Benjamin Franklin, volume XI, 518-520.
  - Account of Money, received from the Commissioners of the United States for their Use; Paris., 1777; 1 vol.; Franklin Benjamin
    This volume of 47 pages was kept by William Temple Franklin, grandson of Benjamin Franklin, and parts were audited periodically by Benjamin Franklin and John Adams, who signed the pages audited. Entries are for expenditures such as laundry; shoe buckles; "Wheel Wright for Work done for Mr. Deane;" wages for servants; "Nine hundred Glass Bottles for the Burgundy Wine;" blacksmith work; "Dinner for some Americans at Versailles when Mr. Adams was presented to the King;" etc.
  - Ledger A and B, 1730-1740; 1 vol.; Franklin Benjamin
    This is the earliest known surviving Franklin account book. It was kept by Franklin and his wife, Deborah, and very few entries are in other hands. Paper was expensive and ruled books were especially dear: therefore, Franklin used the last half of this volume for Ledger B. "Leidger A" (Journal) is the front half of the book and the entries are records of sales, purchases, printing expenses, bills, etc., under the date of the transaction, and then they were posted under the name of the customer in "Leidger B" (Ledger). Beginning with page 169 the Ledger entries follow, recording individual customers' accounts. There is an eight page index which precedes this Ledger and Franklin, by November 1736 had used all of the pages in the back of the book, so he then used the blank pages between the Journal and the Ledger, and numbered the pages from front to back. Franklin noted that he had cancelled all of the accounts by March 5, 1757, that were either "settled or not like to be recovered." Some of these were "Carried to Ledger E" See: George Simpson Eddy, Account Books Kept by Benjamin Franklin: Ledger 1728-1729, Journal 1730-1737.
    The Papers of Benjamin Franklin, volume I, 172-175.
  - Ledger D, 1739-1748; 1 vol.; Franklin Benjamin
    This large (ca. 400 page) volume contains entries for credit sales but few payments, for legal forms, paper, ink, quills, etc., much like Ledgers A and B. Also, it contains records of dealings with many public officials of Philadelphia and the governors of Pennsylvania, Delaware and New Jersey. See: G. S. Eddy. Account Books Kept by Benjamin Franklin. Ledger D, l739-1747. New York: 1929.
    The Papers, of Benjamin Franklin, volume II, 232-234.
  - Memorandum book, 1757-1776; 1 vol.; Franklin Benjamin
    This volume was kept by Deborah Franklin to record her expenditures while Franklin was overseas. After his return in 1762 Franklin kept the entries in this volume. He listed, generally, his major transactions and did not include his petty cash payments. She listed everything she could recall spending.
    The Papers of Benjamin Franklin, volume VII, 167-168.
  - Post office book, 1748-1752; 1 vol.; Franklin Benjamin
    "Post Office Book, 1748, May 25" This volume of 372 pages records receipt and dispatch of all mail in the Philadelphia Post Office between May 25, 1748 and July 23, 1752. Deliveries into the Post Office from out of town were listed, letter by letter, by the names of the addressees, weight and amount due, paid or free. Outgoing mail was simply listed by number of sheets and weight, not by individual letters.
    The Papers of Benjamin Franklin, volume II, 182-183.
  - Account book, Franklin and Hall, 1752-1766; 1 vol.; Franklin Benjamin
    This volume contains four separate lists pertaining, to David Hall's management of the Franklin & Hall partnership. Three of these lists are of cash payment for publishing and the fourth is an inventory of Franklin's shop at the commencement of the partnership. 1.) Record of Money received by Hall for advertisements In the Gazette [Jan. 26, 1748-Jan. 17, 1766]. 2.) Record of advertisements, blanks, &c., printed for ready cash [Jan. 26, 1748]-Jan. 28, 1766. 3.) Accounts of Money received by David Hall for printing work... commencing Jan[ua]ry. 21st. 1748. 4.) Invoice of Books &c. left in my Hands by Mr. Franklin, taken January 23d. 1748.
    The Papers of Benjamin Franklin, volume III, 270-271.
  - Account of Administration of Benjamin Franklin's Property in Philadelphia, by his great grandson Dr. Franklin Bache, and his great great grandson Dr. Thomas Hewson Bache, 1820-1874; 1 vol.; Franklin Benjamin
    This large, thick volume of ca. 400 pages contains entries of rents from tenants of the houses which Franklin built facing Market Street in Philadelphia; interests on mortgages; repairs to houses; payments to heirs; etc.
  - "Post Office Leidger No. 1", 1737-1742; 1 vol.; Franklin Benjamin
    This volume of less than 100 pages is an index of names under their initial letter and dated entries following each name showing charges and payments received. The unpaid accounts were "Carry'd to New Ledger." - Ledger No. 2.
    The Papers of Benjamin Franklin, volume II, 178-179.
  - Philadelphia [Post Office Ledger, No.2], 1742-1753; 1 vol.; Franklin Benjamin
    The balances due Franklin from unpaid postage in "Leidger No. 1" are entered here and many people owed Franklin money. Some of the accounts are marked "Paid" and some have a line drawn through them, possibly indicating "Paid." Such outstanding entries due Franklin were entered in "Ledger E." This Post Office Ledger, No. 2, is a large ledger of ca. 325 pages.
    The Papers of Benjamin Franklin, volume II, 179-180.
  - Philadelphia Post Office Record Books. No. 3., 1743; 1 vol.; Franklin Benjamin
    "Post Office Accounts drawn out Nov. 1743" is a small volume of ca. 50 pages. It contains a list of names with amounts due with notes as to letters delivered, paid, etc. The names are abstracted from Post Office Ledger, No. 2.
  - Post office account book, wrapped in vellum, 1748; 1 vol.; Franklin Benjamin
    "Post Office Accounts" May 18, 1748, is the continuation of the above ledger. It contains 68 pages.
    The Papers of Benjamin Franklin, volume II, 180-181.
  - Post office book, March 30, 1757-October 1764; 1 vol.; Franklin Benjamin
    Franklin, in 1757, appointed his wife's nephew-in-law, William Dunlap, to succeed William Franklin as the Philadelphia postmaster. This volume of ca. 90 written pages lists the letters received at the post office and may well supply a fair picture of the colonial postal system with Philadelphia as a focal point.
    The Papers of Benjamin Franklin., volume VII, 158-160.
  - Post office book, (list of names), [ca.l74l]; 1 vol.; Franklin Benjamin
    "List of Lettars in the Post Office," lists unclaimed letters which were, most probably, the dead letters found in any post office. This volume is ca. 50 pages.
    The Papers of Benjamin Franklin, volume II, 181.
  - Shop book, 1737-1739; 1 vol.; Franklin Benjamin
    This volume contains the same kind of entries as "Leidger A" (Journal) and most of the entries herein were made by Deborah Franklin. Since these entries overlap with those in "Leidger A" (Journal), it is sensible to assume that the entries were made in whichever volume proved more convenient at the time, with Franklin more likely to use the Journal and his wife the Shop Book. Most entries appear under date of transaction. From the Shop Book and "Leidgers A & B" a good picture of Franklin's business activities emerges. His printing ventures, goods sold over the counter in the shop and items for his business use or resale give an insight to the struggles to get ahead in the world, for he sold everything from ink and quills to printed legal forms and books.
    The Papers of Benjamin Franklin, volume II, 127-128.
  - Bank deposit book with Smith, Wright, and Gray, Bankers, London, 1734-1774; 1 vol.; Franklin Benjamin
    This volume contains Franklin's account with the London banking firm of Smith, Wright & Gray. It is a small volume which lists his deposits, withdrawals and drafts during his second mission to England as agent for Pennsylvania.
    The Papers of Benjamin Franklin, volume XI, 179-180.
  - Ledger, 1764-1775; 1 vol.; Franklin Benjamin
    "The Ledger of Benjamin Franklin containing Accounts of such Transactions only as have pass'd since his leaving Philadelphia Nov[embe]r 7. 1764 and during his Residence in London" is a volume of 71 facing pages of debit and credit entries with individuals or businesses, etc., and contain the date, a brief description of the transaction, and the amounts of each. This "Ledger" is to be used in conjunction with the "Journal; 1764-1776," for they were "put in order" by Jonathan Williams, Jr., Franklin's grandnephew and Franklin kept both volumes thereafter.
    The Papers of Benjamin Franklin, volume XI, 5-8-520.
  - Cash book, 1772-1778; 1 vol.; Franklin Benjamin
    This is a cash book, with a title page: A Petty Cash-Book, (Properly Ruled, Titled, and interleaved with blotting Paper) for Compact Accounts, or Minutes, of Receipts and Payments of Money, for Housekeeping, Pocket-Expences, or Any other Family or Personal Concerns, which require A small and cheap Book: To which are prefixed Necessary Explanations and Directions for such Persons as are not conversant in Accounts. London: n.d.
    Franklin entered herein freight of books from Edinburgh, charcoal, frame-maker, coach hire, letter, telescopes, messengers, "To a poor Artist who offer'd some Machines which he thought useful to America," etc. on the credit side and the debits are listed as "Cash in hand," Received on Saturday...," "'Rec'd of V. T. Franklin the Ballace of the Money furnish'd by Mr. Adams for the Expence of his Journey to Dieppe for which I am Dt to Congress," etc.
  - Waste Book. Account of Money Transactions, Receipts and Disbursements In France, December 3, 1776-March 10, 1779.; 1 vol.; Franklin Benjamin
    This small volume of 11 pages was kept by Benjamin Franklin and his grandson and secretary, William Temple Franklin. The old gentleman listed his expanses from landing in France to his arrival in Paris; money sent to his friend, Samuel Vaughan, of London; carriage rentals; advances to "a German Officer to help him on to one of the sea Ports;" "laundry;" "cleaning the Rooms;" etc.
  - Account of Money received from the Commissioners of the United States for their use, 1777; 1 vol.; Franklin Benjamin
    This volume was kept by someone other than William Temple Franklin, although some entries are in his hand and he examined it, Sept. 14, 1778 and wrote: "Delivered a Copy of the Above Accounts to Mr. J. Adams this Day to be examined and settled." Adams, B. Franklin and Silas Deane's accounts for wine, "Coffee House for Letters, &c," servants wages, blacksmiths, "expenses when at Versailles," laundry, etc.
  - Account of family expenses, 1779; 1 vol.; Franklin Benjamin
    This vellum bound volume, which contains ca.30 pages of writing, was kept by William Temple Franklin for his grandfather, Benjamin Franklin, while they were in France. Benjamin Franklin examined it occasionally and signed it as being correct. These are purely personal expenditures for laundry, dinners, stationery, servants wages, "Paid for Musick (being the Day the Declaration of American Independence was celebrated)" pocket umbrella, books, cords of wood, etc. This is a copy, in part, of No. 22. It is not the account book containing Benjamin Franklin's signature, but his signature is copied on the correct pages.
  - Account of family expenses, 1779; 1 vol.; Franklin Benjamin
    This vellum bound "Account of Monies received from Benjamin Franklin Esquire (for the purpose of paying the Family Expenses) of ca.55 pages was kept by William Temple Franklin. The expenses included tavern accounts, books, coachmens wages, servants wages, stationers accounts, etc.
  - Account book, 1782; 1 vol. (on floor C); Franklin Benjamin